<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophy on STEEM@dapeng</title>
    <link>https://steemit.netlify.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Philosophy on STEEM@dapeng</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://steemit.netlify.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of useless - 庄子说：假如我是头猪</title>
      <link>https://steemit.netlify.com/post/use-of-useless-or/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 10:34:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steemit.netlify.com/post/use-of-useless-or/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;原文链接: &lt;a href=&#34;https://steemit.com/cn/@dapeng/use-of-useless-or&#34;&gt;steemit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cnsteem.com/cn/@dapeng/use-of-useless-or&#34;&gt;cnsteem&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://chainbb.com/cn/@dapeng/use-of-useless-or&#34;&gt;chainbb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://busy.org/cn/@dapeng/use-of-useless-or&#34;&gt;busy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/pzhaonet/steem_mirror/master/content/post/use-of-useless-or.md&#34;&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, my wife picked some wild garlic chives from the botanic garden and cooked it for dinner. My elder son J asked, &amp;lsquo;is it grass?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explained to him the difference between grass and vegetables. &amp;lsquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t eat anything wild that you don&amp;rsquo;t know, not only wild vegetables, but also meat. Pork, mutton, chicken are good for our health. That is why we eat them. Why don&amp;rsquo;t we eat the meat of rats or squirrels? They are not tasty or good to out health&amp;rsquo;, I talked a little further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J said, &amp;lsquo;then rats or squirrels are lucky. They can live longer than those eaten by us.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of a Chinese Philosopher, Master Zhuang, who  lived 2400 years ago. He once told a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, some villagers  wanted to cut a big tree so as to build a house. The tree was already hundreds of years old. However, the most experienced carpenter in the viilage said that it was not a good idea because the tree was absolutely useless. If the tree were useful, it would have been cut long time ago and could not have been still living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the night, the carpenter had a dream. The tree said to him in the dream, &amp;lsquo;why did you say that I am useless? Well, I am not useful to humans, and this is just why I can survive. I am useful to myself. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand this, you are the one who is useless.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows the use of useful, but does anybody know the use of useless?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.publicdomainpictures.net/pictures/200000/nahled/pigs-1478813226qX0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@eduter 在&lt;a href=&#34;https://cnsteem.com/cn/@eduter/3ey314&#34;&gt;心理疾病&lt;/a&gt;里写到：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;庄子说，假如我是头猪，与其我被喂的饱饱的并打扮的漂漂亮亮的送上祭坛，我还是更愿意脏兮兮地在泥巴地里打滚和捡东西吃。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;其实庄子没说过这句话。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;庄子虽然没说过这句话，但这句话里蕴含的哲理确实来自庄子。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;有一次，孩子妈去植物园割了一些野韭菜，给我们做晚饭。大娃京生得知这韭菜不是超市买的，而是从草地上割来的，就问：”这是草吗？”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我意识到，爱国主义和科普教育的机会来了，于是放下筷子，开始长篇大论：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“这是个好问题。你看，中文的草，菜，药这三个字，都是草字头。很久以前，这三种东西长在一起，长得很像，人们分不出来，饿了不会吃，有病不会治。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;后来，有个叫神农氏的人，中国人哦，很勇敢，冒着生命危险自己去品尝，尝了100种，分出了哪些好吃又健康，就叫做菜；哪些不好吃或者有毒不能吃，就叫做草；哪些能治病，就叫做药。小朋友分不清，在外边玩的时候不能乱吃。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;不光是菜哦，肉也是。我们为什么吃猪肉，牛肉，羊肉，鸡肉，不吃狼肉，狮子肉，大象肉呢？很久以前，人们花了很多时间去试，才挑出了这些好吃的健康的肉；那些我们平常不吃的肉，就是不好吃或者不健康的，小朋友不要乱吃。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;京生想了想说：”那狼，狮子，大象真是很幸运，没被人吃掉，能活的时间长。”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我觉得，儿子这简短一句话的价值，秒杀我前面啰里啰唆说的一切。因为他自己悟出的这个道理，是庄子的观点。庄子讲的故事是这样的：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从前，有个木匠，路过一棵大树，看上去非常粗壮茂密，树龄有几百年了。大家说，这树砍了盖房子多好。木匠却说，这棵树肯定没用；要是有用，早就被砍了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;木匠夜里做梦，这棵树对木匠说：“你凭什么说我没用？我对人来说没有用，但我能保自己的命，这就是最大的用处，连这个都不明白，你才没用呢。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;庄子原话是这么说的：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;山木，自寇也；膏火，自煎也。桂可食，故伐之；漆可用，故割之。人皆知有用之用，而莫知无用之用也。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我孤陋寡闻，“无用之用”我到高中才第一次听说，听说的时候还觉得豁然开朗。如今，却被7岁的儿子轻易点破了。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>五毛钱的点赞 Upvote of Fifty Cents</title>
      <link>https://steemit.netlify.com/post/upvote-of-fifty-cents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 08:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steemit.netlify.com/post/upvote-of-fifty-cents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;原文链接: &lt;a href=&#34;https://steemit.com/cn/@dapeng/upvote-of-fifty-cents&#34;&gt;steemit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cnsteem.com/cn/@dapeng/upvote-of-fifty-cents&#34;&gt;cnsteem&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://chainbb.com/cn/@dapeng/upvote-of-fifty-cents&#34;&gt;chainbb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://busy.org/cn/@dapeng/upvote-of-fifty-cents&#34;&gt;busy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/pzhaonet/steem_mirror/master/content/post/upvote-of-fifty-cents.md&#34;&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I got my delegated 1000 SP back from @justyy. It has been 7 days since my application. He complained to me and asked why I withdrew the money and asked if he did something wrong. Nothing. The only reason was that I was not rich. No extra money to save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;昨天，我存到 @justyy 银行里的 1000 SP 终于全部取出来了。从发起申请算起来，花了 7 天。银行行长哀怨地问我为何不存了，是不是他做错了什么。没有啊，取钱的理由很简单：手头太紧，钱不够花。这年头，地主家也没有余粮啊，更别提我了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently I have only two thousand Steem powers. My voting power is usually 20% - 30%. I boasted in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://steemit.com/cn/@dapeng/steem-cn-project-hope-2017-10-04&#34;&gt;CN Welcome Center Plan&lt;/a&gt; that I will support new Steemians. However, an upvote of mine was worth only several cents. With the 1000 SP back, one upvote will be worth 0.5 SBD when my VP is 100%. I still remember that I bought a beer to celebrate my post which got 0.5 SBD for the first time.  The cheapest beer costs 0.5 SBD in the supermarkets of the city where I am living in. Now a new steemian will be treated with a beer if I upvote. Somehow, it reminds me of the film &lt;em&gt;Shawshank Redemption&lt;/em&gt; . Andy risked his death to treat his desperate prisoner friends with three beers, which gave them the happiest time and hope  in the sunshine. More or less, I think I have Andy&amp;rsquo;s joy, if only for a short while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我的 SP 总共只有两千多，平时的 VP 一般维持在 20% - 30% 左右。就这点家底，我还在“&lt;a href=&#34;https://steemit.com/cn/@dapeng/steem-cn-project-hope-2017-10-04&#34;&gt;希望工程&lt;/a&gt;”里口口声声宣称要扶助新人。每次给新人点个赞，只值几分钱。我觉得，至少得上 1 毛钱，才拿得出手。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;现在好了，收回这 1000 SP 后，当我 VP 满血的时候，100% 点赞大约有五毛钱。当初，我的文章收益第一次达到 5 毛钱的时候，特意去买了瓶啤酒庆祝。—— 0.5 SBD，够买一瓶廉价超市最便宜的啤酒。现在，我成了五毛党。只要我给新人点一下赞，就等于请他们喝了一瓶啤酒。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不知怎的，这让我想起了电影 &lt;em&gt;Shawshank Redemption&lt;/em&gt; (肖申克的救赎)：安迪冒着死的危险，为那些绝望的狱友们赢来了每人三瓶啤酒的犒赏。在阳谷的沐浴下痛饮这三瓶啤酒，是他们最大的享受。而我，享受的是安迪的快乐，哪怕只有片刻。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rcj2GoIbFHk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youtube video: The Shawshank Redemption Beer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I talked about this,   @tvb said, sadly, that her upvote was only worth 5 cents. I said &amp;lsquo;Xiangruyimo&amp;rsquo;. This is an old Chinese phrase, originated from Master Zhuang,  a philosopher who lived 2400 years ago. He told a story about fishes in a spring which was dried up. The fishes had to moisten one another by their saliva so as to survive. New steemians with few SPs are called small fishes on steemit board. What a coincidence!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当我在新人 QQ 群里说起这事儿的时候， @tvb 哀怨地说，她的 SP 全算上，点赞也就 5 分钱。我说，那我们就“相濡以沫”吧。我觉得，“相濡以沫”用在 steemit 上，是非常贴切的一个词。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@victorier 曾写过&lt;a href=&#34;https://steemit.com/cn/@victorier/7hnr9e&#34;&gt;相濡以沫真的只止於這四個字嗎?&lt;/a&gt;一文，介绍了这个成语。成语来自庄子，说的是两条小鱼在一个干涸的泉眼里快要死了，只好吐出泡沫抹在对方身上，才能生存。steemit 上的那些新人，恰恰被称为小鱼。这是巧合吗？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Master Zhuang said, it would be better for the fishes to forget one another in the rivers and lakes. I was wondering when steem grows to a large lake so that we can forget one another one day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;庄子还说；相濡以沫，还不如回到江湖里，俩俩相忘。只要日子过得好，总比死在一起强。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;那么，啥时候 steemit 才能发展成一条大江呢？steemit 上的小鱼大鱼们，我们啥时候才能相忘于江湖呢？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://steemitimages.com/DQmeYUwQ7Juorgd79o6D5E34BnUYxwfmLxYH4cApgPRhRf6/end2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;大鹏观察&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>